Individually catalogued manuscripts, 1591-2005 Various call numbers
Lilly Library
Individually catalogued manuscripts
1591-2005
Lilly Library
Various call numbers
160 Items
- Langworthy family letters, 1874-1885
  General
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11179118
  Conditions Governing Access
  This collection is open for research.
  Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchase: 2010
  Biographical / Historical
  Merchant G. W. (George Washington) Langworthy (1816-1893) was born in Ballston Spa, Saratoga County, New York. He became a merchant in Worthington in Greene County, Indiana, becoming a dealer in dry goods, clothing and carpets.
  Scope and Contents
  Collection consists of letters by and to Langworthy family members. The primary correspondents are George Washington Langworthy, Sr.; George Washington Langworthy, Jr.; and Lyman Perkins Langworthy to Abigal Jones (nee Langworthy). Letters detail business dealings and events related to life in Greene County, Indiana. Merchant G. W. (George Washington) Langworthy (1816-1893) was born in Ballston Spa, Saratoga County, New York. He became a merchant in Worthington in Greene County, Indiana, becoming a dealer in dry goods, clothing and carpets.
- Miniature shorthand Bible - Abraham Bassano, 1655
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/13541029
  Purchase: 2013
  Miniature shorthand manuscript of the Old and New Testament, in hand of Abraham Bassano, 1655. "The Old & New Testament ... after Sheltons first short hand Book"--P. [1]. Ruled in red. Bound in brown leather, with gilt decorations, marbled endpapers, gilt edges.
- Glaubensbekenntiniss, 1863
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9968646
  Gift: 2010
  A bound German language holograph collection of personal reflections on faith and other religious themes such as prayer, confession and baptism. 1863 marked the 300th anniversary of the formation and adoption of the Heidelberg Catechism which was celebrated in both Europe and America. This appears to be a personal reflection in response to the tercentenary celebrations. Bound in pebbled green cloth, with gilt lettering on front cover, gilt edges.
- Latta genealogy newsletter, Issue 38, 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11653048
  Gift: 2009
  The Summer 2009 issue of The Latta genealogy newsletter, which is published approximatedly three times a year. The bulk of the newsletter is dedicated to accounts of individual family members oral history accounts, family anecdotes, reproductions of photographs and corresponence, and a newspaper article transcription. Individuals so described in this issue include James T. Latta, John Donald Latta, and Frank Latta. Additionally, the newsletter publishes the family trees and related anecdotes of two branches of the family (Branch 18 and 27) and notes and queries related to the Latta family. It includes reports, the budget, and other material related to the Latta Genealogy Society, the non-profit organization that funds the newsletter and Latta family research, and its administration.
- Langworthy family letters
  Collection consists of letters by and to Langworthy family members. The primary correspondents are George Washington Langworthy, Sr.; George Washington Langworthy, Jr.; and Lyman Perkins Langworthy to Abigal Jones (nee Langworthy). Letters detail business dealings and events related to life in Greene County, Indiana.
- World War I German and Austrian Vivat-Bänder collection, 1914-1917
  Gift: 2007
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11667483
  Collection consists of Vivat-Bänder. These strips of silk, which derive their name from the Latin fama semper vivat ("may his fame last forever") and Bänder (German, "ribbons"), were printed at the suggestion of a physician as a fundraiser for military medical aid. The examples shown in this collection, produced by a select group of artists, depict significant victories and generals as well as members of the imperial families. With this collection there is also a publisher's printed description with an English translation.
- Two German WWI postcard albums, 1916-1918
  Gift: 2012
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12083795
  Collection consists of two postcard albums from soldier Josef Held to his family in Munich. The postcards were sent from the field in Poland and Russia during from 20 June 1916 to 10 August 1918.
- Ruhleben Camp illustration, 1910s
  Purchase: 2007
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767878
  One drawing illustrating life in Ruhleben Camp. An individual in the foreground is carrying a large box full of food, and in the background undifferientiated individuals queue before an office. Signed in corner: FW. Ruhleben Prisoner of War Camp was a civilian detention camp in Ruhleben, Germany during World War I. The majority of the prisoners were British, and many of them were taken prisoner because they were in Germany due to travel, school, or work at the outbreak of World War I. The prisoners largely administered their own internal affairs, and they had active art, theater, music, and sports groups.
- Map of the 32nd General Hospital in WWII, 194-
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11667616
  Map depicting the movements of the 32nd General Hospital throughout World War II. Events, places, and people are illustrated with small etchings. "Showing locations, dates and routes of travel beginning with commission ceremony at Indiana University School of Medicine and terminating with demobilization of troops at Camp Atterbury." The 32nd General Hospital was an Army hospital unit organized by doctors and nurses at the Indiana University School of Medicine. The doctors and nurses were officially inducted into the Army on May 13, 1942, and the unit was activated on January 15, 1943 in Texas. Many of the doctors, nurses, and dentists hailed from Indiana, although the enlisted personnel in the unit were from across the United States. They were stationed in England from September 1943 to May 1944, and then they were transferred to France. The 32nd General Hospital was the first Allied general hospital in France after D-Day, and they were stationed in Normany between August and November 1944. In November, they were placed on inactive status and transferred to Belgium; subsequently, it was reactivated and stationed in Germany between March and July 1945. The hospital closed on July 30, 1945, and during that summer and fall of 1945 unit personnel made their way back to the United States. The 32nd General Hospital was official deactivated in October 1945. Map was owned by Crystal Halstead (1911-2006) of Muncie, IN. Halstead was a nurse in the nursing corps during WWII.
- Loewenberg diaries, 1930-1970
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767899
  Four typed transcriptions of diaries of the Loewenberg family; the bulk of the diaries describe life in Germany during and after the Nazi regime and World War II. The first diary, a computer printout (ca. 1970s), is titled Homeless in exile: days of persecution in fall and winter, 1938-39. It is by Harry Richard Loewenberg, written at the behest of his daughter, Barbara, and chronicles his life in 1930s Germany and emigration from Germany to England. Barbara's historical annotations about the fate of individuals and events after her father's return to Germany are incorporated into the typescript. The second, third, and fourth diaries, all ca. 1970s, are photocopies of typed transcriptions. The second diary is written by Peter Christian Loewenberg and is addressed to his own sons. It recounts his life in Germany throughout the war and in its immediate aftermath, including working under the Organisation Todt and the British army. The third diary, largely from Peter Christian's point of view with one section narrated by his wife, Irma, describes life in Germany after the war, emigration from Germany to the United States, and the first days of their lives in Connecticut. The fourth diary consists of anecdotes about Peter Christian's experiences as a practising physician, both in Germany and in Connecticut.
- Dictionary of National Biography, 1906
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8444759
  Lilly Library copy is grangerized by the addition of twenty-four autographed letters, six photographs, and three engravings. The former owner who grangerized these volumes is not known, but a number of letters are addressed to Charles Oliver and several letters in the collection are addressed to "Cousin Charles" and are signed by a "Cousin Lucy," one of which reads: "your affec. cousin, Lucy Oliver."
- Tomáš G. Masaryk travel photographs, 11 Mar.-29 Apr. 1927
  2008.0
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8591245
  Black and white travel photographs with dates and/or location information written or typed on the verso of each of the photos. The photos chronicle Masaryk's travels from Southern France (visiting such cities as Aix-en-Provence, Nîmes, Arles) to Egypt (visiting such cities as Luxor, Cairo, Alexandria, Giza). Among the photos of Egypt are several of archaeologist Howard Carter (taken with President Masaryk) on the site of the Tutankhamun excavation ("Tut-Anch-Ammonova") and several of British Egyptologist, Cecil Mallaby Firth (taken at "Sakkâra u Kahýry"). The photos of Jerusalem feature historic sites and cities such as Bethlehem, the Milk Cave, Nazareth, the Dead Sea, and the Mount of Olives. Other photos document Masaryk's stops in Jordan, Palestine, and Greece (pictures includes Athens, Delphi, Corinth, Mycenae, Epidaurus, Thyrins, Corinth, and Olympia). The photos in this collection are dated from March 11 to April 29, 1927.
- Diary of Grimod de la Reyniere, 1794-1795
  Purchase: 2014
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/14014207
  Autograph diary written in de la Reyniere's hand in brown ink; each page with entries for between four and seven days. Written in Paris and Montmélian: 1 July 1794 to 1 April 1795. The diary is started during the Terror, just before the fall of Robespierre in July 1794. The diary covers a particularly significant period in de la Reyniere's life, just after the death of his father, the arrest of his mother by revolutionary forces, and his return to Paris after an absence of some years. The diary foreshadows his future as an influential food and restaurant critic and writer, a genre he founded and formed with his contemporary Jean Anthelme Brillat-Savarin (1755-1826). The diary provides insights into the core of Parisian society and the contemporary world of the revolutionary period. The diary entries reference visits to the Palais Royal, where Grimod and his group ate, socialized and dined at the Cafe de Chartres (today known as Le Grand Véfour). Also mentioned are promanades across the Pont Neuf, in the rue Montmartre, the Tuileries, the Champs-Élysées, and other Right Bank locales.
- A letter to Monsieur Van. B---- d'M---- at Amsterdam, 1688
  Purchase: 2011
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9968678
  Manuscript copy of A Letter written by Denzil Holles (see Wing H2462), copied in 1688 by an unknown person: "London, coy'ed [sic] out AD: 1688."
- Maria of Castile payment authorization, 1426
  Purchase: 2012
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11551238
  Manuscript leaf in medieval Catalan from Maria of Castile authorizing Johan de Masquillem, Court Treasurer, to pay thirty gold florins to pere de Vallseca. Vallseca (probably Eduardo de Vallseca) was a faithful player of stringed instruments or harp of the King's palace and was granted the money for the diverse services which he has performed.
- Roll of Spanish prisoners of at Fort St. Felipe 1751-1781
  2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981741
  An alphabetical list of name of prisoners held in Fort St. Felipe. The handwritten list covers both sides of the sheet, lists alphabetically 95 names of men taken prisoner at the fort St. Felipe. The lists begins with Don Antonio Reverte and Don Ricardo Montero. There are pencil annotations on the list; the names are in a copperplate hand and listed alphabetically with the most distinguished of the prisoners listed first. It is unclear whether this list is related to the Seven Years' War.
- German manuscript travel journal to Switzerland, 1895
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12544256
  Consists of a manuscript travel journal, with the cover tilte "Meine Schweizer Reise, 1895," containing an account of 70 days of travel to and in Switzerland, in narrative form, illustrated with original photographs and printed illustrations, and embellished with original botanical specimens including a rare Edelweiss flower. Text is in German and contains 60 photographic illustations, 3 of which are in color, 9 of which are flanked with authentic flora. Illustrations vary in size from 3 x 4 cm to 9 x 23 cm. The journal documents a trip from Gera on 16 September 1895 through Heidelburg, then to Konstanz before going on to Lucern where the traveler has placed a rare Edelweiss flower and pictures of the area. Continuing to travel through Bern, Interlaken, Ouchy, Montreux, Vernuyaz, and Chamonix in Switzerland. Then the traveler moved to Martigny in France and then to Geneva in Switzerland, where the traveler stays for 17 days before moving to Neuchâtel, Colmar in France and Frankfurt am Main in Germany before returning to Gera.
- Lady Florence Baker letter, 13 Oct. 1880
  Purchase: 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8095085
  Long holograph letter (3 leaves ([12] full pages)) signed, to Mrs. Malcolm, reporting on her visit to Japan ("this extraordinary country"), describing her journey from Nagasaki to Kobe, but mainly discussing Kobe itself. Lady Baker (née von Sass) was probably born in a German-speaking region of Hungary, although her early life is shrouded in mystery. She was made a refugee in the Hungarian Revolution of 1848, and afterwards kidnapped by the Ottomans and raised in a harem. In 1859 she was offered for sale in a market of enslaved people in Widden on the Danube. There she was acquired by the explorer Samuel (later Sir Samuel) Baker (1821-1893), later to be famous for his African adventures, notably a failed attempt to discover the source of the Nile (1862-1865) and a four-year stint as commander of the khedive of Egypt's expedition to annex territory and abolish the slave trade south of Gondokoro (1869-1873). Lady Baker accompanied her husband on all of his travels; they embarked on a world tour in 1880-1881.
- Thaddeus Lowe war report, 1863
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11683773
  A manuscript copy of Lowe's war report to the Secretary of War. It covers his complete service as the Chief Aeronaut of the Union Army Balloon Corps (1861-1863), incorporating letters to Lowe from various generals, letters to Lowe from members of the Balloon Corps, and reports by Lowe. In several different secretarial hands, with additions, deletions, and corrections. Lowe's manuscript notes and signature are scattered throughout.
- William H. Carroll's Civil War diary and military records, 1863-1998
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11653004
  Items related to William H. Carroll's service in the 24th Indiana Infantry Regiment during the Civil War, including a manuscript diary, his 1863 discharge form, and copies of National Archives records relating to his 1865 disability discharge and pension. [1] Carroll's diary is a daily account of his life in the 24th Indiana Infantry Regiment between March 16, 1863 and December 18, 1863. It includes his account of the Battle of Port Gibson on May 1, 1863, the Vicksburg Campaign and the Siege of Vicksburg, and the Siege of Jackson. In the back of the diary Carroll kept an account of his clothing and supplies. At the beginning and end of the volume are penciled accounts, many unlabelled and others related to crops and farming, and manuscript notes, all presumably from a later date. [2] The discharge paper of William H. Carroll, dated 31 December 1863, at Algiers, Lousiana "by reason of Reenlistment as Veteran under G[eneral] O[rder] 191 Series of 1863 War Dept". [3] A photocopy of a transcribed family letter about the Carroll family in the nineteenth century ([2] p.). [4] Photocopies of research material related to the 24th Indiana Infantry Regiment ([4] p.). [5] Copies of Carroll's pension records from the National Archives (1863-1891), which include affadavits concerning his disability discharge and his widow's attempts to claim his pension ([28] p.). [6] Twenty original photographs, including a tintype, of individuals from the Carroll family in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries; no. 8 is tentatively identified as William H. Carroll.
- Captain Addison Lee Ewing's Civil War diary and related items, 1862-1865
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8760799
  Collection includes six items: [1]. Capt. Addison Lee Ewing's handwritten diary (106 p.), dated Feb. 1864-Apr. 1865, with lengthy and detailed entries of his experiences during the Civil War. The diary entries include Ewing's experiences as Commander of Company I, 63rd Indiana Regiment, of the battles they go through, of events (such as attending a "Negro dance"), of the end of the war, and of the death of President Lincoln. Ewing goes to see Lincoln's corpse in the East Room of the White House, and then goes to the funeral, viewing Lincoln's body at the Rotunda of the Capitol. Finally, and just before he leaves the Army and goes home, Ewing is invited by Indiana Governor Morton to pay their respects to President Andrew Johnson. [2]. Included also is a typed transcription (303 leaves; 29 cm.) of several of Capt. Ewing's diaries, including the one in this collection, dated from Feb. 3, 1862 to Apr. 29, 1865. [3]-[4] Two documents showing his promotions to 1st Sergeant (dated 17 July 1862; 25 x 39 cm.), then to 2nd Lieutenant (dated 2 Oct. 1862; 35 x 26 cm.). [5]-[6] Finally, included is a miniature tintype photo in a gold-tone frame (as well as a print of the picture on photo paper, measuring 90 x 65 mm.) of Capt. Ewing.
- Woodrow Wilson letter, 30 Sept. 1914
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981826
  Typed letter (1 folded leaf ([2] p.)) signed, from President Woodrow Wilson to Indiana Senator John W. Kern, Sept. 30, 1914, regarding Wilson's opinions about the reelection of Indiana Senator Benjamin F. Shively.
- James Lilley's arithmetic book, 1812-1819
  Purchase: 2015
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/15229880
  "The text of the patent refers to a new and improved "Compass" that is "intended to facilitate calculation of oblique-angled trigonometry and finding the area of triangles." This codex begins with James but 10 years old, as he begins arithmetic instruction under Mr Tilford. The volume continues with Lilley's voluminous notes for the next seven years, covering a number of mathematical topics, from Subtraction, Dry Measure, Apothecaries Weight, Compound Division, Of Rebate or Discount, Inverse Proportion, A General Rule for Extracting the Roots of All Powers, Promiscuous Questions, etc. This is followed by a 2II ledger for Lancaster Schoolhouse, then a 5ll ledger for Surry Farm, then a 10ll general ledger. Next are 4ll recording family births & deaths beginning with John Lilley [b. 1772] to James Campbell Lilley [d. 1901 (some later entries obviously recorded in a different hand)]. Next are Lilley"s 6 leaves of pen trials, with the repetition (21x, in this instance) of such phrases as "Contention and Strife make uneasy our life James Lilley 1820." The volume concludes with 43II of geometry & land survey problems, cases, etc, dated 1823-1824. A fascinating, unique primary source documenting this individual's mathematical schooling [including current thought & practice], as well as local county history & family genealogy." -- Bookseller's description.
- Henry H. Durham letter, 29 Nov. 1852
  2009.0
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981723
  Holograph letter (1 sheet ([4] p.)) signed, written by Parke County resident H. H. Durham to his future wife, Susannah Newlin, written in response to a letter of Nov. 21th 1852. It contains news of people and activities in Park County, Indiana at the time.
- Persian playing cards for the game of "Âl Nas", ca. 1850-ca. 1950
  Gift: 2008
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8521513
  Cataloger supplied title. The collection consists of 8-10 different sets of Persian playing cards ranging in date from ca. 1850-ca. 1950. Several of the cards (ca. 1850-1900) include portraits of Nasir al-Din Shah Qajar. Some of the cards display the rather typical Qajar "farangi" style (i.e., a fascination with European subjects such as women in décolleté). One card is tooled leather (or imitation leather) on wood. Description based in part on information from Christiane Gruber, professor of Islamic Art, Department of the History of Art, Indiana University, 10/07/09. Âs Nas is the game from which poker may have developed, and its earliest record dates back to 17th century Persia (see "Cards Without Traditional Suits, Âs Nas, https://web.archive.org/web/20090221095236/http://playingcards.freewebpages.org/cards79.htm). The majority of the cards bear hand-painted images such as the Sarbaz (the soldier), the Padishah (the king), the Bibi (the queen), animals, and flowers. Accompanied by a hinged red vinyl covered wooden box (ca. 1950?). In the lid of the box is a lacquered panel (6 x 23 cm.) illustrating a hunter, two Caspian tigers, three hares, and three gazelles.
- Sam Loyd letter, June 1896
  2010.0
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11344520
  Autographed letter, dated June 1896 in New York, from Sam Loyd to Mr. Raynor opining that Raynor's puzzle would not succeed because it is too similiar to previous puzzles, specifically the "15 Block puzzle" for which Loyd claimed credit. Loyd talks at length about what makes a new puzzle successful and marketable, and he gives advice on how one should enter the puzzle trade.
- German tangram problems, ca. 1850-1899?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9849422
  19th century bound collection of 40 hand-drawn and illustrated (in black, white and greys) picture problems and 11 problem figure outlines. Images include people, buildings, and architectural adornments. The leaves are hand numbered (leaves 45-48 are blank); the only other writing in the volume appear on the recto of the front free endpaper (former owner's mark, "Wotton, 17 Cavendish Sqre"), recto of the front free endpaper ("Edee"(?)), leaf 32 ("fish woman"), and leaf 44 ("tea pot"). The former owner could be Henry Rendell Wotton. The Calendar of the Royal College of Surgeons of England 1874, lists a H. Rendell Wotton, residing at 17 Cavendish Square, London, as a member (a Fellow since Feb. 14, 1856). Henry Rendell Wotton, surgeon, is listed as a resident of 17 Cavendish Square in Boyle's Fashonable Court and Country Guide, and Town Visiting Directory Corrected for 1857. A pencil sketch of a man in 19th century dress (a double breasted overcoat) is drawn on the verso of leaf 46; a sketch of a man's face appears at the top left-hand corner of leaf 8.
- Anonymous cryptographic manuscript, ca. 1780, 1867
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9095201